And next up we have David Wright.
David.
Is that looking all right?
Looking great. Thank you.
All right.
I'll try and keep it brief
so we can have some time for questions.
And that's not an excuse by me, but
this is more of a proposal, less a paper.
My name is David Wright.
I'm an associate professor
at University of Bergen in Norway, but
I'm currently in a hotel room in Dublin
because I'm doing research
on Samuel Beckett's correspondence.
My plan is to make a Samuel Beckett robot.
And I'm also doing a project on
found historical
media and documents that feel like AI
but aren't.
But this project, digitally speaking,
the disfiguring the canon
came about from this poem,
which is by Philip Larkin.
And I'll stop by reading the poem
that note you hold, narrowing
and rising shakes like New Orleans
reflected on the water and in all areas.
Appropriate falsehood wakes
building for some legendary quarter
a balconies, flower baskets and quadrilles
everyone making love and going shares
o play that thing
glorious story bills others may license
grouping around their chairs.
Sporting house girls
like circus tigers priced far above rubies
to pretend they're fads.
While scholars manque has not around
unnoticed, wrapped up
in personals like old plays on me.
Your voice falls.
As they say love should like an enormous
yes, my Crescent City
is where your speech alone is understood
and greeted as the natural noise of good
scattering, long haired
grief and squad pity.
This is a poem by Philip
Larkin called For Sidney Bechet,
and it's about the clarinet player
Sidney Bechet,
who was born in New Orleans
but mostly worked in France.
And I'll play a little bit.
As you can hear, there's
a very unique style with which he plays.
It's got a very strong vibrato,
and I was interested
in giving this to an LLM and saying,
analyze this poem
and then interpret it without words,
and this is what it came up with.
And there was something
there is a sense of vibrato
that's transferred from the poem
into this weird digital work
that I asked an LLM to produce
that sort of transfers from the original.
So you've gone from music
to poetry to a weird digital
LLM AI created thing.
I kind of see this as similar
to a phrase this,
or kind of a digital like phrases,
which Mitchell describes.
He has this idea of three phases
expressing indifference, hope,
and despair.
The first stems
from the common sense perception
that it is impossible
that words can sight but never sight.
And I guess that does happen here.
The second hope is similar to Calvin's
hope for a better understanding
and control of the visual imagination
that would accustom us
to control our own inner vision
without suffocating it or letting it fall
into confused, ephemeral daydreams.
He argues that in this phase, at phrases
ceases to be a special or
exceptional moment in verbal or aural
representation, and begins to seem
paradigmatic of a fundamental tendency
in all linguistic expression.
He goes further, arguing that underpinning
hope is a central goal of overcoming
otherness.
This stage, Mitchell continues,
inevitably leads to a third phase,
which he labels a frantic fear
a moment of resistance, or counter
desire, that occurs
when we sense that the difference
between the verbal
and visual representation might collapse,
and the figurative imaginary
desire of phrases might be realized
literally and accurately.
It is the moment in athletics
when the difference between verbal
and visual mediation
becomes a moral, esthetic imperative.
I also saw this as a way of
applying Gilbert Bugs
idea of machine vision.
She talks about.
She mentions the idea of August,
a giant with a hundred eyes
he could see in all directions at once,
and he never stopped watching,
even when he slept.
Only some of his eyes were closed.
Human vision is far more limited.
We have
just two eyes in the front of our heads
and can't see what is behind us at all.
We see what is straight ahead of us
clearly,
but our peripheral vision is poor.
Many other animals have eyes on the sides
or even on the backs of their heads.
Some species can see infrared
and ultraviolet light.
Humans cannot.
We can see only in the rather limited way
that our eyes, brains and bodies enable.
And yet, for sighted humans,
vision is the primary way
we make sense of the world around us.
Humans have used technology to expand our
limited vision for millennia.
I then have this
very perverse idea of taking Bloom's
canon, which he divides into for ages,
and having an LLM or various
llms generate me a visual representation
of the literary text without any words,
and to see what it kind of came up with.
And it gets a bit
weird for today's purposes,
I've taken three texts The Egyptian
Book of the dead, The Divine Comedy,
and Madame Bovary, and I've used two llms
one is ChatGPT, the other is Deep Sink.
And as you can see,
they each have their own kind of flavor.
So this, for example, is
ChatGPT interpreting
the Egyptian Book of the dead.
And here is deep sea doing the same thing.
Here is
Dante's Inferno by ChatGPT,
which is kind of weird.
I kind of gave it some limitations.
Chapati was very kind of like,
we don't have enough space to do this.
And I said, we'll make it happen anyway
because I sort of gave it
parameters of publications like taper.
And then this was deep six
odd abstract
interpretation of the Divine Comedy.
And then this is Madam Bovary by
ChatGPT here and deep here.
And it's very abstract.
It's not very literal at all.
And I suppose I want to finish today
with just three questions.
What would this tell us?
I tell you about specific llms
machine vision.
As you can see, different llms
have a different kind of flavor to them.
What would this tell you
about the concept of the Western canon,
which is something that I think
is contested and needs to be interrogated?
And how do we read the visuals?
To the latter question,
I kind of see it seems to almost
want to do this
kind of abstract expressionism
to to the interpretive machine
interpretation of a literary text,
and we all finish it there so we can have
some more time for questions.
Thank you.